Register of the T. G. Stepanov-Mamaladze writings
Hoover Institution Archives
T. G. Stepanov-Mamaladze writings
1985-1998
2000C91
Stepanov-Mamaladze, T. G.
5 manuscript boxes (2.0 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Diaries and notes, relating to Soviet foreign relations, and to Georgian politics and foreign relations. Includes summaries of conversations between Eduard Shevardnadze and foreign leaders. Also available on microfilm (10 reels).
Administrative Information
Access
Microfilm use only.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2000.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical/Historical Note
Teimuraz G. Stepanov-Mamaladze was born in 1934 in Tbilisi (Georgia). After graduating from the Moscow State University Law School in 1958, he began his career as a journalist in Georgia. In 1978 he was appointed director of the Georgian Information Agency (Gruzinform). At that time he met Eduard Shevardnadze, the first secretary of the Communist Party of Georgia. In 1985, when Shevardnadze was appointed minister of foreign affairs of the Soviet Union and left for Moscow, he invited Stepanov-Mamaladze to work as his aide and speechwriter, which he did through 1991.
In that capacity Stepanov-Mamaladze traveled extensively on various diplomatic missions, including the summit meeting between Gorbachev and Reagan in Reykjavik (1985), talks on the intermediate range nuclear forces treaty (INF) in 1987, and arrangements surrounding the end of the Soviet occupation of Afghanistan. He witnessed the tearing down of the Berlin Wall in Germany, the "Velvet Revolution" in Czechoslovakia, and the overthrow of Nicolae Ceauşescu in Romania in 1989. Stepanov-Mamaladze also accompanied Shevardnadze during negotiations with Saddam Hussein on the brink of the first Gulf War, when the Soviet Union tried to give the Iraqi leader the opportunity to leave Kuwait honorably in 1991, and was at Shevardnadze's side during meetings of the UN General Assembly from 1986 to 1989.
Stepanov-Mamaladze sat next to Shevardnadze when the latter met with Ronald Reagan, George H. W. Bush, George Shultz, James Baker, Ayatollah Khomeini (who had met with only two foreign diplomats - Eduard Shevardnadze and Yasser Arafat), and Hans-Dietrich Genscher, to name just a few.
After Shevardnadze retired from his position as minister of foreign affairs (1991) and was elected to the presidency of the Republic of Georgia in 1992, Stepanov-Mamaladze became his assistant.
In 1994 Stepanov-Mamaladze decided to resume his work as a journalist. He returned to Moscow, where he wrote for Komsomol'skaia pravda, Izvestiia, and Novye izvestiia newspapers. He became the head of the Novye Izvestiia Agency board of directors and a member of the Consultative Council of the Pro et Contra magazine under the auspices of the Carnegie Foundation.
He died in 1999 in Moscow and was buried, according to his wishes, in Tbilisi.
Scope and Content of Collection
The collection contains Teimuraz G. Stepanov-Mamaladzes's diaries and notes taken in his capacity as aide to Eduard Shevardnadze when the latter was the minister of foreign affairs of the Soviet Union from 1985 to 1991 and during the first two years of his presidency of Georgia. Stepanov-Mamaladze took notes during all the negotiations, meetings, and conferences he attended, thus creating an extensive record of Eduard Shevardnadze's diplomatic endeavors.
In 1992 Shevardnadze visited the Hoover Institution and notes on that trip can also be found in Stepanov-Mamaladze's notebooks.
The notes in the Notebooks series are especially interesting because they present summaries of conversations between Eduard Shevardnadze and foreign leaders. The notes were taken on the spot, thus preserving lively conversations and jokes made by participants. Sometimes they include poems by Stepanov-Mamaladze, anecdotes, and quotations from books by famous authors.
The notes laid a foundation for the Diaries, which were written without haste, and present the same events in a more detailed and comprehensive way.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into two series: Notebooks, 1985-1998, and Diaries, 1985-1990.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Soviet Union Foreign relations 1985-1991.; Georgia (Republic) Politics and government 1991-; Georgia (Republic) Foreign relations 1991-; Shevardnadze, Eduard Amvrosievich.
Collection Contents
- Notebooks, 1985-1998. (Box 1-4, Reel 1-8)
  Includes 121 notebooks of notes taken during meetings of Eduard Shevardnadze with foreign leaders, along with some personal notes.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - circa 1985 (Envelope 1: 1, Reel 1)
  - 1985 October 2 - 26 (Envelope 1: 2, Reel 1)
  - 1985 November (Envelope 1: 3, Reel 1)
  - 1986 January 15 - 21 (Envelope 1: 4, Reel 1)
  - 1986 February 7-March 15 (Envelope 1: 5, Reel 1)
  - 1986 March 17 - April 25, 1986 July 13 (Envelope 1: 6, Reel 1)
  - 1986 April 30, 1986 May 27; 1986 September 12; 1986 October 2 (Envelope 1: 7, Reel 1)
  - 1986 June 6 - July 2 (Envelope 1: 8, Reel 1)
  - 1986 September 18 - October 2 (Envelope 1: 9, Reel 1)
  - 1986 October 18 - December 16 (Envelope 1: 10, Reel 1)
  - 1986 November 3 - 5 (Envelope 1: 11, Reel 1)
  - 1986 December 19, 1987 January 3 - 4; 1987 February 2 - 5 (Envelope 1: 12, Reel 1)
  - 1987 January 5 (Envelope 1: 13, Reel 1)
  - 1987 January 5 - February 2 (Envelope 1: 14, Reel 1)
  - 1987 February 7 - March 3 (Envelope 1: 15, Reel 1)
  - 1987 March 2 - 7 (Envelope 1: 16, Reel 1)
  - 1987 March 10 - 13 (Envelope 1: 17, Reel 1)
  - 1987 March 16 - April 6 (Envelope 1: 18, Reel 2)
  - 1987 April 28 - May 11 (Envelope 1: 19, Reel 2)
  - 1987 May 11 - 20 (Envelope 1: 20, Reel 2)
  - 1987 May 20 - June 9 (Envelope 1: 21, Reel 2)
  - 1987 June 13 - 18 (Envelope 1: 22, Reel 2)
  - 1987 June 18 - 21 (Envelope 1: 23, Reel 2)
  - 1987 July 1 - August 4 (Envelope 1: 24, Reel 2)
  - 1987 July 13 - 16 (Envelope 1: 25, Reel 2)
  - 1987 August 5 - September 10 (Envelope 1: 26, Reel 2)
  - 1987 September 13 - 27 (Envelope 1: 27, Reel 2)
  - 1987 September 30 (Envelope 1: 28, Reel 2)
  - 1987 October 1 - 16 (Envelope 1: 29, Reel 2)
  - 1987 October 16 - 26 (Envelope 1: 30, Reel 2)
  - 1987 October 30 - November 24 (Envelope 2: 1, Reel 2)
  - 1987 November 27 - December 31 (Envelope 2: 2, Reel 2)
  - 1988 January 2 - 17 (Envelope 2: 3, Reel 3)
  - 1988 January 19 - March 9 (Envelope 2: 4, Reel 3)
  - 1988 March 11 - April 3 (Envelope 2: 5, Reel 3)
  - 1988 March 28 - April 13 (Envelope 2: 6, Reel 3)
  - 1988 April 14 - May 25 (Envelope 2: 7, Reel 3)
  - 1988 June 1 - July 22 (Envelope 2: 8, Reel 3)
  - 1988 July 25 - August 6 (Envelope 2: 9, Reel 3)
  - 1988 August 8 - September 25 (Envelope 2: 10, Reel 3)
  - 1988 October 3, 1988 October 7 (Envelope 2: 11, Reel 3)
  - 1988 October 10 - November 14 (Envelope 2: 12, Reel 3)
  - 1988 November 15 - December 3 (Envelope 2: 13, Reel 3)
  - 1988 December 3 - 18 (Envelope 2: 14, Reel 4)
  - 1988 December 20 - 23, 1989 January 3 - 7 (Envelope 2: 15, Reel 4)
  - 1989 January 7 - 18 (Envelope 2: 16, Reel 4)
  - 1989 January 19 - February 3 (Envelope 2: 17, Reel 4)
  - 1989 February 3 - 17 (Envelope 2: 18, Reel 4)
  - 1989 February 17 - 18 (Envelope 2: 19, Reel 4)
  - 1989 February 20 - 22 (Envelope 2: 20, Reel 4)
  - 1989 February 24 - March 7 (Envelope 2: 21, Reel 4)
  - 1989 April 9 - 13 (Envelope 2: 22, Reel 4)
  - 1989 April 13 - 19 (Envelope 2: 23, Reel 4)
  - 1989 May 12 - 17 (Envelope 2: 24, Reel 4)
  - 1989 May 18 - June 13 (Envelope 2: 25, Reel 4)
  - 1989 June 14 - July 18 (Envelope 2: 26, Reel 4)
  - 1989 July 28 - August (Envelope 2: 27, Reel 4)
  - 1989 August 5 - September 16 (Envelope 2: 28, Reel 4)
  - 1989 September 21 - October 2, 1989 November 2 (Envelope 2: 29, Reel 4)
  - 1989 October 4 - November 28 (Envelope 2: 30, Reel 4)
  - 1989 November 29 - December 8 (Envelope 3: 1, Reel 4)
  - 1989 December 17 - 28 (Envelope 3: 2, Reel 5)
  - 1990 January 3 - 11 (Envelope 3: 3, Reel 5)
  - 1990 January 12 - February 4 (Envelope 3: 4, Reel 5)
  - 1990 February 5 - 13 (Envelope 3: 5, Reel 5)
  - 1990 February 13 - March 17 (Envelope 3: 6, Reel 5)
  - 1990 March 18 - 21 (Envelope 3: 7, Reel 5)
  - 1990 March 22 - 26 (Envelope 3: 8, Reel 5)
  - 1990 March 28 (Envelope 3: 9, Reel 5)
  - 1990 April 5 (Envelope 3: 10, Reel 5)
  - 1990 April 6 (Envelope 3: 11, Reel 5)
  - 1990 April 10 - May 5 (Envelope 3: 12, Reel 5)
  - 1990 May 5 - 23 (Envelope 3: 13, Reel 5)
  - 1990 May 8 - June 11 (Envelope 3: 14, Reel 5)
  - 1990 July 11 - 14 (Envelope 3: 15, Reel 5)
  - 1990 July 16 - 30 (Envelope 3: 16, Reel 5)
  - 1990 October 18 - November 17 (Envelope 3: 17, Reel 5)
  - 1990 November 19 - 28 (Envelope 3: 18, Reel 5)
  - 1990 November 29 - December 14 (Envelope 3: 19, Reel 5)
  - 1990 December 14 - 30, 1991 January 2 (Envelope 3: 20, Reel 6)
  - 1991 January 4 - February 22 (Envelope 3: 21, Reel 6)
  - 1991 February 22- March 18 (Envelope 3: 22, Reel 6)
  - 1991 March 18 - April 11 (Envelope 3: 23, Reel 6)
  - 1991 April 12 - May 6 (Envelope 3: 24, Reel 6)
  - 1991 May 6 - 17 (Envelope 3: 25, Reel 6)
  - 1991 May 18 - 30 (Envelope 3: 26, Reel 6)
  - 1991 June 8 - August 15 (Envelope 3: 27, Reel 6)
  - 1991 August 18 - September 6 (Envelope 3: 28, Reel 6)
  - 1991 September 10 - 23 (Envelope 3: 29, Reel 6)
  - 1991 September 23 - November 25 (Envelope 3: 30, Reel 6)
  - 1991 November 25 - December 11 (Envelope 3: 31, Reel 6)
  - 1991 December 13 - 31, 1992 January 2 - 30 (Envelope 3: 32, Reel 6)
  - 1992 February 2 - 20 (Envelope 3: 33, Reel 7)
  - 1992 February 21 - March 18 (Envelope 3: 34, Reel 7)
  - 1992 March 20 - April 21 (Envelope 4: 1, Reel 7)
  - 1992 April 23 - May 25 (Envelope 4: 2, Reel 7)
  - 1992 May 25 - June 4 (Envelope 4: 3, Reel 7)
  - 1992 June 5 - 14 (Envelope 4: 4, Reel 7)
  - 1992 June 15 - July 5 (Envelope 4: 5, Reel 7)
  - 1992 July 16 - 28 (Envelope 4: 6, Reel 7)
  - 1992 July 29 - August 29 (Envelope 4: 7, Reel 7)
  - 1992 August 31 - September 22 (Envelope 4: 8, Reel 7)
  - 1992 September 25 - November 3 (Envelope 4: 9, Reel 7)
  - 1992 November 4 - 17 (Envelope 4: 10, Reel 7)
  - 1992 November 24 - 31, 1992 January 6 - 30 (Envelope 4: 11, Reel 7)
  - 1993 February 11 - March 12 (Envelope 4: 12)
  - 1993 March 12 - May 6 (Envelope 4: 13)
  - 1993 May 6 - June 4 (Envelope 4: 14)
  - 1993 June 7 - July 16 (Envelope 4: 15, Reel 8)
  - 1993 July 16 - August 6 (Envelope 4: 16, Reel 8)
  - 1993 August 9 - September 16 (Envelope 4: 17, Reel 8)
  - 1993 September 17 - October 3 (Envelope 4: 18, Reel 8)
  - 1993 October 4 - November 21 (Envelope 4: 19, Reel 8)
  - 1993 November 21 - December 29, 1994 January 5 - February 8 (Envelope 4: 20, Reel 8)
  - 1994 February 8 - April 16 (Envelope 4: 21, Reel 8)
  - 1994 April 18 - June 20 (Envelope 4: 22, Reel 8)
  - 1994 September 16 - October 2 (Envelope 4: 23, Reel 8)
  - 1994 December 3 - 31, 1995 January 4 - February 18 (Envelope 4: 24, Reel 8)
  - 1995 March 8 - April 19 (Envelope 4: 25, Reel 8)
  - 1997 January 26 - February 6 (Envelope 4: 26, Reel 8)
  - 1998 March 11 - May 13 (Envelope 4: 27, Reel 8)
- Diaries. Arranged chronologically., 1985-1990. (Box 5, Reel 9-10)
  Includes 9 books based on the notebooks.
  - 1985 August 30 - December 31 (Envelope 5: 1, Reel 9)
  - 1986 January 1 - September 23 (Envelope 5: 2, Reel 9)
  - 1986 September 24 - December 31, 1987 January 1 - June 21 (Envelope 5: 3, Reel 9)
  - 1987 July 23 - December 27, 1988 January 1 - 19 (Envelope 5: 4, Reel 9)
  - 1988 January 19 - August 7 (Envelope 5: 5, Reel 9)
  - 1988 August 9 - December 31, 1989 January 3 - April 9 (Envelope 5: 6, Reel 10)
  - 1989 April 9 - August 5 (Envelope 5: 7, Reel 10)
  - 1989 August 13 - December 31, 1990 January 2 - April 6 (Envelope 5: 8, Reel 10)
  - 1990 April 6 - October 19 (Envelope 5: 9, Reel 10)